all right and now you wanted to do
which linda to go around and talk about
what we
what we think the best foundation is for
starting a community
yes um so
i guess everyone well most people
i feel um like a place to
organize um their their thoughts into
like a place to start
um and a lot of times
places will start with um
a line of bullet points or rules that
are
um kind of govern how the whole
situation
is run and just have a discussion about
whether or not it's even good to have
those
or not and what um
would be the best way to
uh have others kind of be joined
together under some sort of common
umbrella or thoughts or principles you
know
maybe just even a couple um words
or just an idea you know that
that would just be uh common amongst
everyone
so as i was thinking about this um
i was thinking that probably using
like rules would be uh not a good idea
because that that's kind of like could
be looked upon as like aggressive and
you might be punished if you break them
so that probably wouldn't be a really
good idea
and um that kind of is how game a is
situated
and it it it uh kind of
gives this aura of conflict
you know like are you following the
rules are you breaking the rules are you
good are you bad blah blah blah
so i kind of was feeling like more i
would like to just
be part of a community that kind of just
had like
uh a philosophy for it
like um you know here is a place where
everyone you know uh the goal is to
live to live together in peace
and you know support uh happiness
amongst each other
and um work together
as cooperatively as possible
like i think that would just be a really
nice and i feel like that would leave
because i
like many different people i like a
whole variety of people around me
so i feel like that couldn't exclude
anyone
it it it could be people from all ages
all races all ideologies
could fit together under that and it
really
doesn't put too much pressure on are you
doing this are you not doing this but
then again it kind of does in a way
but so you've said in your
little um mission vision statement there
was a lot of different
things in there right to work together
to promote happiness to do
um i think it's helpful to know what
your top prior
your personal top priority is um i have
two
and i'm like they're when i was writing
it down it was um
resiliency like being in a place where i
know we can handle whatever storms come
eating we grow our own food we have
but in an interconnected way that my
current community doesn't have
are that there's a risk that comes with
intertwining your finances but there's
also resiliency that comes with knowing
that your food is is together right
where it's not
every family for themselves and you
abandon ship when there's there's chaos
although that can be
part of it but just knowing that the
resiliency and the intertwined
knowing i don't want our finances 100
intertwined but i also don't want
i want to know my food shelter basic
needs are met by that community
when stuff hits the fence so resiliency
the other one was authenticity and
diversity
that to me i do want that diverse group
of people
but at a higher level i want people who
are authentic where i can show up and be
authentic
and they're able to be authentic and i
know what conflict
comes from that you can't just like
everyone's gonna be authentic
and hope that there's no there's no
conflict because there will be
and then my um my one thing i would form
a community around
i think people either have land and they
want to find people they have people and
they want to find land or they have a
mission right to start a healing center
and my um central thing around which i
want to start a community as a
technology cooperative because i want to
i think that's a great way to fund it
it's my purpose on the planet
and i want those things to find so a
community around a technology
cooperative so that would be what we
have in common and then the values that
i want are
resiliency and and diversity slash
authenticity but they're not resiliency
and then that they're
directly i can't have one without the
other
um i don't know
if i have one yeah i don't know if
there's one
higher prioritized than the other with
mine
i just feel like i know that i would
like to be surrounded by people who
um living
peacefully with each other is important
to them you know
i don't um i like to
com compromise and find solutions to
problems
that everyone can be comfortable with so
even though that doesn't always happen
like i try to
strive for that in my relationships and
i find that
living with people if you kind of
look at the bigger picture and not just
well this is what i want but you kind of
look at the other person and see it from
their point of view
you know also trying to have like
um a holistic
vision of the community a
self-centered vision you know
that that to me would probably be
my um number one
um thing i would want
going on sorry i missed with the peace
happiness what is the number one yeah
you wanted the condition but that's like
yeah a painting of utopia let's agree on
a painting of utopia and every piece of
it and then we will work towards
creating the painting yeah
without knowing what that you know what
i mean like are there
i think a lot of conflict like even even
a peaceful happy place
right well what does that mean to you
versus somebody else does that mean no
conflict does that mean no one ever
raises their voice like what does that
actually mean like what is your highest
value but i may be getting into the
reads i want to hear from daniel and
juan what their
highest values and thing they might
design a community around
or uh
yeah sure i can go unless i'm
interrupting
oh no no i was just gonna say like not
necessarily none of it but when it
occurs
that it's handled in a way that is
um looked at as fa try trying to be as
spirit as possible to everyone
and that people aren't looking at
situations
and how am i going to benefit from this
how am i how is this going to
work for me and forget if it causes you
pain or whatever you know like that like
thinking of others
as you think about yourself too
yeah it sounds like the golden rule
right treat others
as you want to be treated yeah that's
one of those
and i heard another one that was called
the platinum rule let's treat others how
they want to be treated
um it's like okay step up from the
golden rule
um you know i i am interested in this
topic
i haven't spent a lot of time thinking
about my like ideal thing that i'm
shooting for so it's good to you know
hear what other ideas are out there and
just
i guess the point is i haven't spent a
lot of time on that
for myself um i've had some good
experiences
short term in community and some bad
ones
people are really messy that's my
experience
people are messy and sometimes
difficult and so i guess
lately i've kind of backed way off
from community because it hasn't gone so
well for me
um but
i think that um
i think that there are
i have a better idea of some of the
kinds of principles that i think
are really important but i don't have
that main
like uh hey a tech community or a
farming community
or an off-grid community or
um a music community you know i i don't
have that specific
in mind um but i have more of like
uh the principles um
i talk about grace i talk about
forgiveness
being built in because
no matter how long you know somebody my
experience is
eventually someone's gonna let you down
whether they
didn't want to or or they meant to or
you know people are messy and flawed um
so the good experiences i've had
those are like core things that we can
always go back to
and so it's like hey well what we're
doing here we are attempting to
give each other grace uh when we can
and so if a member does something
they you know had a bad moment did
something they regret
then the move is to see if they can
reconcile and see if
um something good can happen from it
whereas if that wasn't a core principle
it appears that
people could go along and not forgive
one another
and then there would cause a lot of rift
and a lot of tension
in a community but as a community or
community leader you wouldn't be able to
say hey well let's go back to that thing
because i could be like i never signed
up to forgive people
like but that's where i think principles
whatever they are
it's like hey well we can kind of go
back this is what we're doing here
um and that's uh
i've got a few different principles that
are kind of like that
and more like character deeper things
that are not so specific i could add the
forgiveness piece
to a bunch of different types of
communities
my thing is i haven't spent the time to
like really dig into
what that is um so yeah that's that
uh and i'll invite juan
to uh share
yes in my case
i am part of a community so um
i can share with you what i was looking
for
and
the most important thing was
to find a community which
is builded by members who take care
of my independence of this community
so the idea in our community is
that we want powerful members in a weak
community
and this means finally
we try to empower every new member
to be more and more independent from
this community
this is my main goal
by searching or founding a community
so i wanted so when people join your
community your goal is to get them to
not need the community
to get them as um resilience the wrong
word
as independent as possible so they know
how to grow their own food they know how
to
fix the solar panels they know how or is
is that what
would you mean by independent from the
community or interdependent from the
rest of the world within the community
now let's uh let's give a sample about
properties
um you see a lot of communities and
because the group of members
doesn't trust other members they invent
the idea
to found an association the association
is a stockholder in the community
every resource with value is
linked to this association a member can
participate
in using this resource as long as he is
member of the community
when he leaves the community he
he lose the access to the resource
in our case when we buy a house or
property
we buy it all the time under the name of
a real
person so one advantage
we see in this behavior is that
every member of the community has
a certain amount of knowledge how it is
to be a member of something so all these
interfaces with the big society outside
uh are handled by everybody
and it's not in the hand of a president
of an
association so there is no hierarchy
needed
and the other thing is if i
collect in a community money to enable
one person to buy a piece of land
or a car or
a flat or a house or whatever
this person know what is the condition
if i leave this community what i lose
and what i don't lose and
this gives me the impression that in our
community
are only people who want to be
in this community they don't need to be
in this community
they don't feel this
[Music]
necessity to to stay
in place even if they don't like to stay
in place
because they they are clear they would
lose
the access to this resource
thank you so when i was out for my walk
this morning
i had this i was thinking because we're
about to have this call
the difference between i've asked this
question to everyone in my community
and not everyone but um like who what
would you design a new community around
and the two answers i've told the story
before the person who was vegan and was
like
they didn't want even though they're a
militant vegan
that they didn't want to community
around veganism and
i believe that's because this vegan in
particular is a militant vegan and wants
to like
convert to other people wants to like
get in on those naughty meat-eaters and
convince them to come vegan which is
very different than the christian guy
who did not answer hey i can help all
the heathens come to christ
it was the opposite it was like no i
don't want a christian community because
what if i had a
conscience if i had a crisis of faith
and then i would lose my community and
my church
i need to have even though i know it's
central to his life and he's
in his you know mid-30s he's not going
to change over
i think is actually 40 anyway that um
the difference between needing
because it would clearly be more
peaceful to have a vegan community if
you wanted a vegan community right
instead of every meal needing it to like
okay accommodate the vegans and figure
out like there's a difference between
needing
everyone to feel your way
after the fact right she's not creating
a world around her veganism because it's
a central part of her life and now we're
gonna have a vegan community
it's no i wanted to i want to be with
and she didn't answer this i'm
making assumptions but be with the
meat-eaters and the omnivores so that i
can
like guilt them into being vegan which
has never made a single person go vegan
of course
and there's something in that in
community where it's like
and game b and all of it and maybe this
isn't the space
but like the people i would imagine i
would want if i wanted veganism in the
world
are the exact opposite of her right it's
the people who who
naturally help people come over help
them eat healthier help them
like without guilting them into it and
um
those are the exact opposite people that
are militant about things sometimes
we're out there like turning people off
of the beautiful life
um it sounds like the the word is
tolerance
because yeah i might have my certain
principles that i think are good and
want to
you know have if i have more of like an
open door community
i need to be extremely tolerant of
people who have different values than me
and like i need to know sort of where
those
end and began for myself
and for a community um i could have a
community
um i mean some of my experience in
burning man there's communities that
have such a huge range of tolerance
for um different lifestyles and
different values
um that it's
it's really cool but it attracts a
big variety of people um and
that's you know it's just all these
different
examples one isn't neither you know
better or worse it's just well it
reminds me of some of the game b
uh stuff that i've heard about when you
set something in motion
you leave open niches and you need to
pay attention to the niches that you
leave
open and be like you know say are these
niches that i want to leave
open and like evolution is going to take
place on whatever you set in motion
and so if you're not aware of those so
if yeah if you start a community
with um you know a a space
of hey we're just vegans here and it's
gonna be
hard if you're not then that's like one
thing
or we're all vegans here and we really
want to have an
open door for people to come and try it
out or experiment
and fail and and come back
or be here and say i can't do it
um oh you know so you're designing
something
up front uh that the people you're
designing it with need to be
on board with probably um
yeah yeah i like because the tolerance
is the piece right
um if we had the conversation beforehand
how tolerant
are we at different meal types then
choosing to be a vegan in a non-vegan
community means you're you're
you need to be tolerant more tolerant
than you would be if that's your number
one concern then you should be in a
vegan community
that there's something about talking
about what that means long before you're
in community because some of these
things you don't know until they arise
it's like oh i didn't realize i was this
confronted by when people
eat meat right but this person's also
lived in community for decades so
she knows she knows that there's
something about that tolerance
that is um
if your if it's tolerance that you're
holding to a higher esteem than that
then it needs to be
front and center right that it's not
vegan tolerant of mediated or immediate
intolerant veganism it's like word
tolerance and this is our main
our main food i don't know if i'm
getting across when i'm trying to like
get into here like the or anyone else
even wants to
the difference in community of knowing
to begin with what
is your
part of that's gonna come from
experience like part of my life has been
joining and experiencing a lot of
different huge variety of different
communities
so um i've got a lot of experience
um and i guess i just mean like life
experience in that sense i've been to a
bunch of different
uh communities and continuing to like
learn from all those um times in my life
so uh but not everybody's gonna
you know has the chance to do that
so
yeah your your goals are going to be
important i mean
even in some of the church communities
i've been a part of
they're they run the gamut they're very
widespread and so
some of them tend to be more like almost
with the vegan thing
uh you're mentioning we're like hey
we're all
uh church people here and we're doing
this church thing
and we don't know how to handle folks
that
are exploring that or just showed up
because their life is falling apart or
something
um because we're all christians here
and that's like a way to do it um i'll
leave my opinions out of it um and then
there's
the the church communities that are like
hey
well you know everybody's at a different
place in their life
and we're extremely tolerant of
um you know whether you're
one of us christians or not
uh that does doesn't really seem to
matter because we're all human beings
but the folks that started that
happen to have a certain world view but
they're like hey well our idea
is to have a bunch of people to work
together and do life with
um so i mean there's another example
that is maybe a little bit analogous
more complicated than the vegan thing
hey
we want to do veganism with open door
tolerance to folk anyone who wants to
show up and hang out and learn
and try it or not or whatever and then
he could be like no we're only doing
this one thing um and
something that juan mentioned was uh
something about trust
which made me think like another thing
on my list
has to do with authenticity and so like
i've had this idea of
uh doing specifically
trust building uh meetings you're going
to start a community
and that authenticity thing you know you
might spend
i i suppose i'm just hypothesizing but
be like we're going to spend the first
six or nine months just doing
storytelling
and just getting to know one another
really well
um which could like you know
weed out the sociopaths or um
something like that and like if that's
something you expect to continue like
you know honesty was mentioned so if if
we're doing trust building
i should be able to go into difficult
um and wonderful but just brutally
honest
parts of my life and talk about them
candidly
and be received um and just heard
because if i'm gonna be in community
long term with these people
then i need to continue to be able to do
that
um and and just be honest hey i failed
at this
or you know hey i dream about doing this
even if it never happens i just need it
to be known
um both of those kinds of things i'd be
curious about
like what trust building um
looks like for uh juan and
your experience with this
i'd be interested to one in a very
particular way
yeah the trust in community like i'm
thinking of like a first date where you
throw all your
bad on the table like if you're
gonna love me love me for this versus
when you're in a relationship long term
and living together there's a bigger
risk to showing up as your real self
because they could leave you over it
there's a bigger risk the longer you're
together and there's something about
that vulnerability
long term versus short term before you
start the community versus in the
community that i've seen come up in my
community
since especially since i don't live
there so yeah trust building
yeah i would say trust building
based on the idea that everything is
handled by communication i think the
first skill is
just to show the other side that you are
able to communicate
and as much as you show the other side
that you are able to communicate on
different levels
by using different channels
you open more doors
for communication
let's take the word you more
um you are laughing a lot
uh if you try to establish a relation to
another person because humor is a very
good vehicle
to transport even ugly or not so nice
messages between people so if you share
a kind of humor between people
um you give the other side
this opportunity to use this
channel later the other thing is
to make it quick it's better to put the
ugly
part on the on the table and in the
discussion
all your nice things you can share later
but to make it short and
not wasting time of others
it is good to be authentic and to
to show you a weak side because
um one main reason for searching for
community
is that you already know your weak side
and you
imagine to find other people who can
substitute this weak part
with a strong better different part
so it makes a lot of sense to come
together and to spend
time together i i have not
experienced that it needs um six months
or more
to to come to this point um
when i think about the last years here
in this house um if you spend
24 hours together if you work together
in a project if you cook together
if you share a bathroom
you you get some information about the
other person
and um i think after one two weeks
you already know more or less the scale
of
possible future relations
sometimes people develop some people
open up
after a certain time but if you stay for
a while
together you um
you you can make up your mind in in a
short time you don't
need so much it's it's my experience
like you know when you get out of
relationship and whatever reason it was
that you got out of that relationship
you then look for a partner that's the
exact opposite of that
and then you like maximize for that
quality and forgetting about all the
other good qualities that i've ever
had that maybe you're not maximizing for
but that is part of what community is as
well right like
like all those people were messy i'm not
like i need to live with people with ocd
like me and then you go and you're like
oh
whoops now everything else falls apart
now i'm the least now i'm the most messy
person in the community
and now they're all on my i'm always
going to be one of the messiest i'm
never going to be a clean person
but yeah that knowing knowing what your
your conflicts are and seeking out
community and then being in
relationship like you're not just going
to leave every time there's a conflict
how do we work this out and how
how does that happen that's what one of
the reasons i love the idea of a meta
community
is that even if your community itself
has
issues in conflict that you can't deal
with you can outs like you can find
other people with better skills or
sometimes you do need a fresh set of
eyes to kind of be more judge and jury
if that
kind of thing is appropriate to be like
hey
neutral third party but yeah but there's
other resources available from a meta
community
than just a physical one
well i'm being a little bit
introspective because i'm trying to
take some things i'm learning and sort
of think about them a little bit
anyways um
i think he froze
no you're just really good at holding
your temple like that oh sure
no my brain froze i lost my train of
thought so
um i was uh also thinking about the
want versus need and how that
um like when you want uh
to start something or you want to be
somewhere
it's a lot easier to
um because need is kind of it gives you
a sense of desperation like if you
needed something you needed it
and then there's more
need to anxiety around it but when you
want to be a part of something
and you and you see the value there then
it's
easier to approach um conflicts and and
different situations that happen with
a more like calm uh
mindset you're not in fight-or-flight
mode because what i need is going to
leave and
you know so now i'm in you know
this state of yeah like uh survival
but when you just want it you get you
can think more
with your um uh logic
and problem solving skills
so i think that's that would be uh good
i i like that
uh in my community i would want to
be remaining at least to the
greater part independent than dependent
you know being dependent on something
kind of scares me
you know so i would like um
that if i if i maintain my independence
then i never truly
need from other people i just want
them so i don't know that's just what i
was thinking about during listening
while listening to everybody
talking
that's an interesting thing to possibly
explore um
next time if we want a topic for next
time is that difference between um
that resiliency like if you're
independent then you can leave at any
time but that also means you're less
likely like
there's a trade-off that i'm seeing in
my community about kobit 19 where people
are dispersing because they can which is
totally valid you're allowed to right
you don't to have
and then what juan was talking about
earlier about having the
he didn't really say like this but
having the rules written out right where
you know what you're you know what
you're taking with you you know what it
means to leave
so that you're free to leave so that you
know you're not starting from scratch
like making sure that
we have the prenuptial agreement in
place that if you leave you know what
you're going with
and it's enough of a
non-barrier that you're free to go
because that is actually the best thing
for community that if
because if you you're forced to stay and
they're forced to keep you
that is the sense of tension that is
hard to
to deal with and yeah this this topic
reminds me of like
uh people being responsible or
the community helping one another to
achieve different types of wholeness
and like i i like the topic of what does
it mean to
start or enter into a community out of
wholeness
or what does it mean to start or enter a
new community
out of um you know need or
desperation or that survival
mentality um which is very real and a
lot of people
are are in that yet they still need
relationships and
we're a society so we need one another
um
but like to what degree is someone
coming in
how do you catch someone as a community
um
who's in survival mode or something like
that
um and the other thing that came to mind
was um
you know one sort of mentioned on oh you
know it
might might not take six months to get
to know someone hey if i spend
48 hours with them and it's quality time
then you know i can really get to know
them well or whatever and you're living
with different people maybe i'm not sure
but
um the other thing that comes to mind
is that um people also
change so you're in community
with um some people but you
should expect them to change their
hobbies might change a little bit their
interests might change because if people
are growing and learning and obviously
if you have kids i mean they're changing
massively
adults aren't changing uh quite as bit
quite quite as much but you know you
need to
leave room for the individuals to
change who they are as they're learning
and growing and exploring new things
in life and like that's related to how
community changes
so this is something i've experienced a
little bit in some burning man groups
that are like hey you know some people
getting nostalgic
and being like hey it used to be like
this and now it's different and is that
good or bad and it's like well it's just
different
and when you have a community i'm
talking about like an
art community that um you know is
is about you know more than 50 people
strong
um and it's going to change over time
and
one of the things i've noticed is that
the community
itself you know it's made up of these
individuals
and you know over the past eight or nine
years
the community has changed because some
people
come and go so you know maybe
someone who was there for you know five
or six
years that brought their personality in
a certain style
and then life happens things change and
and they moved on and that like
that kind of changed the flavor of the
community a little bit because they're a
big personality
but that doesn't mean the community goes
away and new people come
in that are slightly different uh they
have a different personality and
like it's almost like the community is a
sum
total of all these different
personalities
that are there um and the personalities
are going to change as well
um the last roommate that i had uh he
lived here for
almost two years and um yeah
if i expected him to be the same person
that who he was when he moved in
that would be a strange expectation
because he's reading books and he's
experiencing life and
and he should be changing um
as things go on right
one of the um things in my head that i'm
working on
doing a video on at some point in time
is the idea of and i've done several
videos on it actually is the idea of a
normal curve
if anyone's familiar with that
mathematically any any
any measurable trait and i assume any
measurable but non-measurable trait also
falls
along a normal curve so there's an
average that um
part of our problem in society to make
things very binary you're
racist or you're not as opposed to a
spectrum of racism
where it's like wait where along this do
you fall because we all fall somewhere
on it
um as a community what are your
parameters what are the acceptable what
is the acceptable diversity and the
non-acceptable diversity
in in different categories right so um
oh open to everyone no no communities
over everyone
because you know it's like your
cleanliness level you're gonna have
people of very different cleanliness
so we might not be open we might be okay
getting the really ocd people if they're
if they're able to be tolerant of the of
the um more messy people
but we don't want the really really
messy people right or we we're okay with
the really messy people because we're a
chaotic artist
community but we're not okay with with
the people who are going to constantly
make us to clean up right
keeping in mind that humanity exists
along the spectrum
the tinier community is going to exist
along the spectrum and what do we want
that to be and
people change and so even if you're like
listen we're only going to let in people
who are
who are able-bodied and can work 40
hours a week and we're gonna and then
someone gets disabled right like someone
gets in an accident something happens
even if you have that parameter then
what does it mean when someone is no
longer in that parameter do they get
kicked out
or do we make accommodations for them um
that is part of what i come across
in the game b space and just in general
is
there's a certain level of independence
i'm not capable of because of my
disabilities
and i have something different to offer
because of my disabilities as well
but it's like and i know i talked about
the
last time of like i feel like the
community wouldn't want me because of
that and that's not true that's my own
story
but there is a certain amount of well if
you're not physically able to do this
work
there isn't a lot that that a community
is going to need
that's like intellectual or
that i could do right it's like well do
you want me to create game b that's all
i know how to do
oh that's if that's the skill you need
in community
but yeah that um to be as independent as
i can
but also know that my strength is in our
interdependence
that when we come together with the
pieces that we can't do
individually we're a better whole and if
you need people to be a very specific
parameter
that's fine to me but to be transparent
about that and transparent about the
leaving process what happens you're not
in that
sliver it reminds me that we all have
different strengths and weaknesses
and different gifts and uh different
ways that we serve i mean if you think
you're going to enter community and only
be taking
like that's just not gonna be
sustainable
uh in so many different ways um i mean
one of my
experiences as someone who did notice
things like clutter in this in this um
type of artist community um i was more
of like a helper
like people had projects and i could
show up and be like what do you need
help with you know this is fun but i
wasn't really like a starter of
things um so i'd help people with things
but we had workshops and
um people would just leave their tools
out
everywhere and sawdust and all sorts of
things and
since i didn't really have a project of
my own i would just start sweeping the
shop and organizing tools and like when
i showed up that's kind of like what i
noticed and you know some folks that are
wired differently
and they a little bit more chaotic they
could kind of like
live in the clutter and that was normal
for them kind of drove me like a little
bit
didn't drive me crazy but they
appreciated when i
cleaned up but it was just a way that i
could serve and feel like
i was you know valuable um
just yeah way i could i could help out
um and that i truly think that some of
the folks
that were way further on the artist
and they couldn't even do that if they
you know they would have to try very
hard and so you have this
symbiosis of you know these different
gifts coming together they'd have to try
very hard
to like keep the workshop clean because
it was just not the way that they were
um you know wired they sort of lived in
this chaos
and i think that's part of having that
is knowing
knowing what's accepted we clean up
after ourselves and some of us aren't
capable and as long as
people know right if you're the cleaner
and as long as you're not getting mad at
everyone because you know
you're not keeping up to your standard
what goes wrong is
if it goes into this space where i'm
telling
other people too much how they
have to be um and telling them
how they you know this was a specific
community
so you know the parameters
are specific but in that case
me coming and being like hey you all
need to like
clean this up more whatever it bothers
me wasn't really appropriate
but if it was something i could help
with
and you know
in that way i could uh
i could participate but it wasn't about
changing someone else
do we want to um we're getting close to
the end of the hour we want to pick a
topic for next week and then we can put
out more of like to the game b community
that we're getting together this time to
talk about this topic and it will be a
little more
i i liked the whole like survival mode
versus coming in a place of wholeness
or i've already established some
dependence
whereas folks are more dependent or
interdependent
or maybe they're in survival mode and
how does game be receive those
folks um
yeah just exploring that landscape that
you know that comes to mind for me that
was very complex for me to write down
resiliency versus like there's something
there that is
is but it's like just this with all the
subcategory
which is also how i end up doing it
which is why i'm looking for someone
else to be like
resiliency interdependence versus
independence and then you can bring up
wholeness and survival right but does
interdependence dependence work for
people
that's a topic but i don't know
is that enticing to people who weren't
part of this conversation as well that's
just that was
my contribution if someone else has like
hey i'd rather talk about this then
you know hey
we got a thumbs up all right
so if we want to i don't know what we
are doing with these record um
meetings as far as if we are making
notes as to what we talked about i mean
this isn't a board meeting we're not you
don't need agenda here are the
midi minutes so someone can catch up
it's like getting together and talking
about what does it take to live in
community right what does it take to
start a community what is like
having conversations about community and
doing it in a way that hopefully brings
in
it's enjoyable for us and brings in more
people so that
this can grow and we can find people to
you know our our pairs to start
communities with
not in juan's case because we can send
people to one if he wants more
well i want to hear more from juan
really
i mean the things you have to share when
i get introspective
about them and just everybody sharing
everything that they did i get a lot of
value out of this when i
turn around and then try to apply it to
my situation that's what i'm trying to
do
yeah i could add and
underline a little bit what some some
aspects
daniel was saying um uh
just not to return to all all of this
i would like to add now
that i feel happy inside of our
community because i'm not
charged by a kind of responsibility for
the happiness of the other members
so i'm quite happy if
somebody what i see
after a short time is more aspects of
the personality than
aspects of skills or
or development in handcraft or
for thinking or or
changing substitution of values or
things like this
i see in some of
the communities actually under the
circumstances of
kovite 19 a tendency to
use this event
to gather some more energy
for for the community
especially for some leaders or members
or the hierarchy inside of the community
um to facilitate to facilitate their
their their goals
so
i think it's a it's a good idea from
daniel to
think about the relation between a
member
and the community and um
this um was
on my journey to meet a lot of
communities in europe
also a big question how would be
my relation between me and the members
i i see and how would be my relation
between
me and this entity community
in our case it's quite difficult for
people to understand this because
we really try to crash the idea
that familia feliz is something like an
entity
so there is no association there is no
speaker for this association
you can't complain that familia feliz is
doing something wrong
because it's doing nothing if the dishes
are not clean
it's not a question of the community
it's a question of
the person who was cooking or serving
or the last one in the kitchen and
you have to deal with this person
so yeah i think this idea from daniel
to put this as a topic for the next
meeting is quite a good idea because
even for
people who are searching now for
community life
they should have a kind of
answer before they start to search for
communities
reminds me of even just people being
prepared of what they're getting into
even on like emotional resiliency i mean
if i don't have the capacity
to leave dirty dishes in the sink and
have my roommate
confront me about that and i'm going to
have a bad emotional reaction i mean
there's just
there's a whole gamut of of that sort of
thing
that uh yeah folks need to
that's like a personal responsibility
like hey you can't react like that as
this is a
you know not a personal attack or you
know however
it's done
so i just wanna there's it's the same
umbrella but interdependence versus
dependence
or wholeness versus survival mode
which one it's not a thumbs up vote for
one verse the other
wholeness versus survival isn't isn't
without being part of this conversation
it maybe isn't
as um i can you know what both kind of
go together interdependence versus
dependence and with the subcategory of
like that's kind of what we're talking
about right is that
how much wholeness do you bring and how
much wellness can you bring
and yeah and then are we in survival
mode
and how do we can we put them together i
like the wholeness survival mode
thing just because i think wholeness
talks about your like physical
tangible you know where you live your
food situation your clothing
these practical things but it includes
your emotional
wholeness these other parts it's a
bigger word i think
it's also like the wholeness of the
individual and the wholeness of the
community
right there's a fullness i can only
bring as much wholeness as i can if i
can't physically grow
food for myself and my family i can't
bring that to the table
but i can bring my whole ist self to the
table
and as a community if we're able to like
look at those pieces and say what are
the things we're not willing to have as
as what do we need how whole do we need
someone to be before they're here and
what does that mean emotionally
physically
spiritually right like what is that
wholeness and how what are we going to
offer
for anything to help make that wholeness
and yeah i like the wholeness versus
survival
and i don't quite know how to articulate
it so other people can come be part of
it
figure it out yes yes i'm not the
greatest at writing things
daniel do you want to write up a little
blurb as to what you're kind of talking
about with wholeness versus survival
because i think you were the one who
brought it up
yeah i can do that awesome and then we
can put it up to the rest of the
community
i'm going to stop recording now unless
anyone has any other thoughts they want
to
finish up with on the recording
all right i almost ended every time